Guide to the photograph album Vers la Tunisie...Sur le "Kairouan" (A Trip to Tunisia on the Kairouan) AD.MC.043
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Vers la Tunisie...Sur le "Kairouan" (A Trip to Tunisia on the Kairouan)
Circa 1951
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Unknown
Lejeune, Nathalie
AD.MC.043
107 Photographic Prints 107 gelatin silver photographs contained within an album measuring 36 x 25 cm
A travel album of a trip to Tunisia from Marseille on the ship "Kairouan" circa 1950s, containing 107 gelatin silver photographs. Places visited are: Tunis, Carthage, Sidi Bou Said, Nabeul, Hammamet, Monastie, Mahdia, Sousse,El Djem, Gabes, Sfax, Matmatas, Douiret, Djerba, Gafsa, Medenine and Kairouan. Creator unknown.
Excellent condition. No tears or foxing.
Box 043
Arrangement
Collection processed as it was received.
Content Description
A travel album of Tunisia containing 107 gelatin silver photographs as well as clippings and postcards. The journey from Marseille, France to Tunis, Tunisia, was made on the ship "Kairouan". Places visited are: Tunis, Carthage, Sidi Bou Said, Nabeul, Hammamet, Monastie, Mahdia, Sousse,El Djem, Gabes, Sfax, Matmatas, Douirot, Djerba, Gafsa, Medenine and Kairouan. The images focus on historical sites, architecture, mosques, a synagogue and the local population - many of these include Tunisian artisans, market traders and agricultural workers. The clippings and postcards mainly depict orientalist tropes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Nathalie Lejeune, 4 Rue Chateaubriand, 59000, Lille France on 23rd July 2018. Prior provenance unknown.
Biographical / Historical
Creator unknown. Photographs taken during a trip from Marseille to Tunis, circa 1950s. Captions are in French and contain racist and culturally insensitive remarks.
Conditions Governing Access
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact Akkasah: Photography Archive, akkasah@nyu.edu +971 2628 5531
Tunisia; Architecture; Regional/National Dress; Photographic Prints; Matmata, Tunisia; Douiret, Tataouine, Tunisia; Tozeur, Tunisia; Médenine/Madanīyīn, Tunisia; Travel; Lejeune, Nathalie
- The front cover of the album 'A Trip to Tunisia on the Kairouan.', Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref1; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Tunisia
- A map of Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref2; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Maps; Tunisia
- The title page of the album 'A Trip to Tunisia on the Kairouan.' Beneath the title is a photograph of the ship Kairouan., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref3; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Boats/Ships; Tunisia; Transportation; French Writing; Gelatin Silver Prints; Photographic Prints; Water
- Group portraits of men and women on the deck of the Kairouan, with views of the ship setting sail from Marseille with the Palais du Pharo in the background., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref4; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing; Marseille, France; Men; Women; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Head Covers/Veils; Bags/Purses; Cameras; Group Portraits; Palaces; Buildings; Water; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Docks/Piers/Jetties
- Views of Tunisia taken from the ship labeled 'first contact (premier contact)' with a view of the Bay of Tunis., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref5; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Water; Women; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Tunisia; Buildings; Boats/Ships; Transportation; French Writing; Men; Group Portraits; Newspaper Clippings; Streets/Roads; Cars/Trucks; Landscapes; Coast; Docks/Piers/Jetties
- From the top-left clockwise: a view of the Bab el Bahr, and two views of the Al-Zaytuna Mosque., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref6; Unknown; CAP - Compagnie (Alsacienne) des Arts Photomécaniques, Strasbourg & Paris; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Men; Group Portraits; Streets/Roads; Buildings; Doors/Entrances; Statues/Sculptures; Architecture; Landscapes; French Writing; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Tunis, Tunisia
- From left to right: two street views of men and women walking in Tunis, and a postcard of the Youssef Dey Mosque/Al B'chamqiya., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref7; Editions de luxe " Estel" Lavelle & Cie, Paris; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Women; Men; Streets/Roads; Regional/National Dress; Tunis, Tunisia; Group Portraits; Gelatin Silver Prints; Photographic Prints; Buildings; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Architecture; Mosques; Religious Sites; Head Covers/Veils; Postcards
- Postcards of the souk in Tunis., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref8; Editions de luxe " Estel" Lavelle & Cie, Paris; Alain; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Postcards; Men; Group Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Markets; Tunis, Tunisia; Shops; Facial Hair; Street Vendors; Workers; Streets/Roads; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing
- Three views of the Alaoui Museum (now The National Bardo Museum), and a group portrait of tourists walking through Tunis., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref9; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Palaces; Architecture; Buildings; Museums; Group Portraits; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Hats; Men; Women; Streets/Roads; French Writing; Bags/Purses; Carriages/Coaches; Transportation; Furnishings; Paintings; Bárdaw/Bardo, Tunisia; Tunis, Tunisia
- Clippings from printed material of the ancient port and Roman ruins in Carthage., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref10; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Landscapes; Mountains/Hills; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Water; Ports; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Newspaper Clippings; Carthage, Tunis, Tunisia
- From the top-left clockwise: An archaeological site undergoing excavation, remnants of Roman temples, a group of tourists, and two stelae in Carthage., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref11; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Group Portraits; Men; Women; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Bags/Purses; Hats; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Temples; French Writing; Carthage, Tunis, Tunisia
- Top and right: clippings of women and girls. Bottom and Left: Women and girls in Sidi Bou Said., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref12; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Women; Individual Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Head Covers/Veils; Girls; Children; Group Portraits; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting; Newspaper Clippings; French Writing; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Jewelry; Postcards; Sidi Bou Said, Tunisia
- Views and clippings of potters and pottery in Nabeul, Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref13; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Newspaper Clippings; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting; Individual Portraits; Boys; Children; Pottery; Workers; Men; Women; Group Portraits; Buildings; French Writing; Facial Hair; Shops; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Nabeul‎, Tunisia
- From the top left clockwise: a portrait of stonemasons, children working on looms, a crowd at a carpet souk, and a doorway and a postcard of people at a market in a kasbah/ribat., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref14; Unknown; Alain; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Carpets/Rugs; Workers; Shops; Postcards; Markets; Doors/Entrances; Pottery; Forts/Castles; Men; Group Portraits; Architecture; Buildings; Boys; Children; French Writing; Dar Chaabane El Fehri, Nabeul, Tunisia
- Left: a postcard of donkeys at a market. Right: a portrait of a man and a child riding donkeys., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref15; Unknown; Alain; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Postcards; Donkeys; Animals; Men; Group Portraits; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Markets; Tunisia; French Writing; Regional/National Dress; Boys; Children; Transportation; Streets/Roads; Facial Hair
- From the top left clockwise: a fishing net for Tuna, a newspaper clipping of a bride, and a wedding procession in Hammamet, Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref16; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Newspaper Clippings; French Writing; Fishing; Landscapes; Women; Weddings; Individual Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Men; Children; Boys; Group Portraits; Parades/Processions; Events/Occasions; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Jewelry; Hammamet/al-Hammāmāt, Nabeul, Tunisia
- Portraits of people on the coast and the Ribat of Monastir, Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref17; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Newspaper Clippings; Boys; Children; Group Portraits; Water; Coast; Forts/Castles; Architecture; Women; Men; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Hats; Individual Portraits; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Docks/Piers/Jetties; French Writing; Monastir/al-Munastīr, Tunisia
- From the top left clockwise: a postcard of a kasbah/ribat, a portrait of a man leaning on a car, and a postcard of sardine fishing boats in Mahdia, Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref18; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Postcards; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Architecture; Buildings; French Writing; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting; Boats/Ships; Men; Individual Portraits; Docks/Piers/Jetties; Water; Mahdia/Al Mahdiya, Tunisia; Forts/Castles; Fishing
- From the top left clockwise: a postcard of buildings in Sousse, buildings captioned "Moorish house", a postcard of and Mahdia and view of Kairouan., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref19; Unknown; Alain; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Postcards; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting; Landscapes; Buildings; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Architecture; Water; French Writing; Sousse/Sūsa, Tunisia; Mahdia/Al Mahdiya, Tunisia; Kairouan/al-Qayrawān, Tunisia
- From the left clockwise: a group of tourists on the beach, a group of boys, a portrait of a man and a woman on the roof of a STTAS (Société Tunisienne des Transports Automobiles du Sahel) bus and a man fixing a broken down vehicle in Sousse, Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref20; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Women; Men; Group Portraits; Hats; Beaches; Boys; Children; Streets/Roads; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; French Writing; Sousse/Sūsa, Tunisia; Buses
- A page entitled 'The jobs of Tunisians (Les occupations des Tunisiens).' From the left clockwise: clippings of a woman begging, artisans weaving, a postcard of a group of people, and a group at a restaurant (Please note: This material has been digitized in its entirety and contains racist and culturally insensitive remarks)., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref21; Unknown; Alain; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Newspaper Clippings; Individual Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Boys; Men; Children; Group Portraits; Workers; Head Covers/Veils; Women; Restaurants/bars; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Streets/Roads; Palm Trees; French Writing; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Tunisia; Postcards
- An aerial view of the Amphitheatre of El Djem., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref22; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Postcards; Newspaper Clippings; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Landscapes; French Writing; El Djem/El Jemm, Mahdia, Tunisia
- Interior and exterior views of the Amphitheatre of El Djem., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref23; Unknown; CAP - Compagnie (Alsacienne) des Arts Photomécaniques, Strasbourg & Paris; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Postcards; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Architecture; French Writing; Men; Individual Portraits; El Djem/El Jemm, Mahdia, Tunisia
- Views of the oasis in Gabes, Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref24; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Oases; French Writing; Women; Boys; Children; Group Portraits; Gabès/Qabis, Tunisia
- From the top left clockwise: a postcard palm trees in a desert, a clipping of a group of camels at a watering hole, and a portrait of a woman and a child (linked 043_ref24)., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref25; Unknown; Cim - Combier Imprimeur (Jean Combier), Mâcon; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Postcards; Newspaper Clippings; Landscapes; Deserts; Palm Trees; Gelatin Silver Prints; Photographic Prints; Women; Boys; Children; Hats; Group Portraits; Oases; Camels; Animals; Gabès/Qabis, Tunisia
- Views of a body of water and palm trees., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref26; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Gelatin Silver Prints; Photographic Prints; Palm Trees; Water; Landscapes; Tunisia
- Views of a body of water and palm trees., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref27; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Palm Trees; Water; Animals; Landscapes; Tunisia
- Views of carriages and the road on the way to an oasis., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref28; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Carriages/Coaches; Transportation; Horses; Animals; Streets/Roads; Group Portraits; Women; Men; Palm Trees; Tunisia; French Writing
- Views of men and animals operating water pumps/wells., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref29; Unknown; Cim - Combier Imprimeur (Jean Combier), Mâcon; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Postcards; Newspaper Clippings; Palm Trees; Irrigation; Machines; Agriculture/Farms; Men; Workers; Individual Portraits; Camels; Animals; Boys; Children; Group Portraits; Landscapes; French Writing; Tunisia; Water; Signatures
- Left: a postcard of a street view of Tunisia. Right: a postcard of people at a stream., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref30; Unknown; Alain; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Postcards; Streets/Roads; Water; Men; Animals; Regional/National Dress; Buildings; Group Portraits; Palm Trees; Individual Portraits; Tunisia; Signatures
- Left: a newspaper clipping captioned "In Sfax, Mahdia and Monastir, there are sponge fishermen's cooperatives. The diving school in Bizerte has renewed the technique of this maritime craft.". Right: sponges on the coast., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref31; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Newspaper Clippings; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Men; Group Portraits; French Writing; Sfax/Safāqis, Tunisia; Monastir/al-Munastīr, Tunisia; Mahdia/Al Mahdiya, Tunisia; Fishing
- Views of camels throughout Tunisia, including a view of the market at Tataouine., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref32; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Newspaper Clippings; Camels; Animals; Men; Group Portraits; Facial Hair; Mountains/Hills; Regional/National Dress; Tunisia; French Writing; Sousse/Sūsa, Tunisia; Tataouine, Tunisia; Markets
- Left: a postcard of two men praying in the desert. Right: a view of the desert., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref33; Unknown; Cim - Combier Imprimeur (Jean Combier), Mâcon; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Postcards; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Men; Regional/National Dress; Camels; Group Portraits; Landscapes; Animals; Praying; Tunisia
- Views of the Berber underground homes in Matmata., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref34; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing; Architecture; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Houses; Palm Trees; Deserts; Landscapes; Matmata, Tunisia
- Views of the Berber underground homes in Matmata. From the top left clockwise: the entrance to the dwelling, a family living in the dwellings, a courtyard, the master bedroom, and a woman weaving on a loom., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref35; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing; Furnishings; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Architecture; Houses; Men; Individual Portraits; Newspaper Clippings; Women; Head Covers/Veils; Regional/National Dress; Group Portraits; Workers; Matmata, Tunisia
- Views of ruins in Douiret, Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref36; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Boys; Children; Regional/National Dress; Men; Group Portraits; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; French Writing; Douiret, Tataouine, Tunisia
- From the top left clockwise: Three views of Marabout Tombs on the way to Douiret, Hergla, and Gabes., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref37; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Landscapes; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Newspaper Clippings; Buildings; Architecture; Deserts; Mountains/Hills; French Writing; Tombs/Mausoleums; Douiret, Tataouine, Tunisia; Religious Sites; Gabès/Qabis, Tunisia; Hergla, Tunisia
- Page captioned "nomads". Top left clockwise: a postcard of a caravan of camels, a group standing beside a camel, a postcard of women and children beside a tent., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref38; Unknown; EPA (Éditions Photos Africaines), Alger; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Group Portraits; Tents; Deserts; Women; Men; Regional/National Dress; Children; Boys; Girls; Camels; Mountains/Hills; Animals; Tunisia; French Writing; Bedouins; Postcards
- Left: a postcard of a snake charmer surrounded by a crowd. Right: a postcard of people at a market., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref39; CAP - Compagnie (Alsacienne) des Arts Photomécaniques, Strasbourg & Paris; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Gelatin Silver Prints; Photographic Prints; Palm Trees; Men; Group Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Events/Occasions; Animals; Boys; Children; Women; French Writing; Markets; Postcards; Food
- From the top left clockwise: a group portrait of tourists on a boat, a boy in front of a buildings, a woman at a well, and a mosque on the island of Djerba., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref40; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Men; Women; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Smoking; Cigarettes; Group Portraits; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Buildings; Architecture; Water; Head Covers/Veils; Regional/National Dress; Individual Portraits; Boys; Children; French Writing; Djerba/Île de Jerba, Tunisia; Mosques; Religious Sites
- Two views of the El Ghriba synagogue and two views of a hotel that "serves as a hotel for pilgrims during major Jewish holidays" on Djerba Island., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref41; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Men; Carpets/Rugs; Individual Portraits; Synagogues; Religious Sites; Furnishings; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing; Hotels; Women; Workers; Architecture; Djerba/Île de Jerba, Tunisia
- From the top left clockwise: a woman and man holding hands, a group portrait at an oasis, two views of the Great Mosque of Gafsa, and Roman baths., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref42; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Hats; Men; Women; Streets/Roads; Buildings; Palm Trees; Architecture; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Donkeys; Boys; Children; French Writing; Mosques; Gafsa/Qafşah, Tunisia; Religious Sites
- Views of the ghorfas of Medenine, Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref43; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Camels; Animals; Streets/Roads; Architecture; Buildings; French Writing; Médenine/Madanīyīn, Tunisia
- Views of mosque architecture, including the the Great Mosque of Kairouan/Mosque of Uqba in Kairouan, Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref44; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Newspaper Clippings; Religious Sites; Mosques; Men; Group Portraits; Architecture; French Writing; Kairouan/al-Qayrawān, Tunisia
- Views of the Zaouia of Sidi Sahab (Barbier Mausoleum) in Kairouan, Tunisia., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref45; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Mosques; Religious Sites; Buildings; Architecture; Children; Women; Head Covers/Veils; Group Portraits; Men; Individual Portraits; Praying; French Writing; Religious Sites; Kairouan/al-Qayrawān, Tunisia; Tombs/Mausoleums
- Two group portraits of tourists preparing for departure from Tunisia, and a view of the Tunisian coast from a ship., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref46; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Men; Women; Group Portraits; Cameras; Boats/Ships; Water; Transportation; French Writing; Tunisia; Hats; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Coast
- The inside back cover of the album 'A Trip to Tunisia on the Kairouan.', Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref47; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
- The back cover of the album 'A Trip to Tunisia on the Kairouan.', Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref48; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
- Left: a postcard of the oasis in Tozeur. Right: a clipping of a man next to a camel from a french missionary., Circa 1950s; AD_MC_043_ref49; G. Fouquet; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 043)
  Photographic Prints; Camels; Animals; Men; Group Portraits; Buildings; Palm Trees; Oases; Postcards; French Writing; Tunisia; Newspaper Clippings; Tozeur, Tunisia